When we write, we put barriers on ourselves that we don't put on ourselves when we speak.
Is that true?
Well yes, because when you write, you are already formulating something.
So you make choices.
There you go, that’s why psychoanalysis exists.
Besides, I think that this debate on writing with L is a false debate.
That the real question first is to know what story you have to tell, how
can you tell it and at the end will you put your signature at the bottom?
of the page? Whatever your age, first of all you have a story to tell, you have something
thing to do, you can change your life, you can pursue your dream even at 60, even
when no one believes it.
If you want to get to the next door there, you have to push the first one.
What my grandfather had taught my father was, he takes the car,
he takes the whole car apart, you put it back together.
That's how you learn.
Today, you can't really do it with Teslas.
You see, technology is neither bad nor good in itself.
It is not neutral either, we know that very well.
But on the other hand, to what extent does it bring me anything compared to
what's wrong with me? Because she always takes something from you.
Hello, it's Réy. I am very happy to welcome you today with a guest
quite exceptional who is called Benoît Raphaël.
Hello Benoît, how are you?
Hello Emy. Well listen, it makes me very happy to be with you today.
We are both live from Bali right now live even if you
you watch us on video later.
Um do you have a little word before we start, before I introduce you, do you have
a little word to say to the audience.
So it's a show in any case that talks about AI but also about geopolitics and geopolitics
today at the heart finally I think of all the current themes.
So I think there was a place that was missing so that's good.
Thank you so much. Thanks to you anyway.
You are the first guest in a long list.
We're really not going to just make a podcast, we're really here to make one
hundred. That's the goal.
Uh listen, I'm very happy to have you for different reasons.
We're going to lay our cards on the table today.
We have Pokémon cards by the way, I'll tell you about them later.
Stay connected. There's something crazy about that.
I I use the terms Jones terms.
People will still believe that I am 20 years old when that is no longer the case.
So I said uh I'm very happy to have you here today because for
several reasons. The first, you are not the best newsletter for me
from France on AI, the best newsletter in the world.
And I'm not telling you this to show off, it's the truth.
really what you did with Génération IA, the newsletters that you send every
weeks, I read them religiously, that is, I always put them as favorites and
I take a time where I only do that, where I cut out everything else.
Besides, very important during this podcast, cut off any source of distraction, eh.
Uh you have to listen because what we are going to say today is super important
for your future, for your work, for your families, for absolutely everything.
The other reason is that, well, let's be honest, we became a little bit friends
here in Bali and in any case, I'm happy.
We've done some cool things recently.
We went to see the film Michael in particular, eh, the King.
I won't ask your opinion on the film because you didn't want to give it.
Um, we all know it’s an exceptional film, but there you go.
And so, suddenly, the presentation, I remember you dancing in front of
the cinema screen, in front of the entire audience.
You dance very well by the way, I was quite Thank you very much.
Well, since then I've made one, perhaps I'll give you an excerpt if the editors
want to put an extract here I will send it to you.
I did one since I did one my first show at the hard rock café in Bali.
It's nonsense. One day I will tell you this story if my career starts.
You never know. Maybe I'll have to tomorrow there will be the Remy Bigo figurine with
his legendary cap. No, that won't work.
So yeah, why is Benoît here today?
because he's someone I follow every day, well at least every week
at least and that I have a lot of pleasure in following and reading.
And what I like about you is that you carry out concrete, real experiments,
not the bullshit we see on LinkedIn or yeah hi, I'm an Intel, I come from there
a week ago, I existed nowhere, neither from Ev nor from Adan, I am unknown to the battalion
and I will offer you the best AI agent which in two clicks will revolutionize you
your business and I find that you are different.
So, can you explain to us a little how you work, why
you are fully on the newsletter today and yeah maybe finish your presentation if
I forgot something important.
Well, already the influencers who tell you in two clicks, you will
create your agent who will solve your business in two strokes of a skin spoon.
I think that we already have to be wary and this is precisely the approach that we
that I try to have with Thomas Ma who is my partner who is the engineer of the
band. It's this duo, it's it's key in fact in the work that we do, it's
that in fact by experimentation when you really test what the famous brilliant thing
that you saw on Instagram or on LinkedIn, in fact you realize that that
doesn't work. So and it's been years since 2023 that we've been told extraordinary things,
this famous AI hype and every time we look at it it doesn't work.
So in fact what we announced 2 years ago now works today.
What we are announcing today will perhaps work in 2 years.
So this approach is actually quite humble, in fact, eh.
We, I am, we are not knowledgeable and it is an approach which is twofold with my
associate who is an engineer therefore in machine learning therefore who knows the technology
so that saves me from talking too much nonsense and with the somewhat rigor of a journalist
and at the same time curiosity.
You are a former journalist by the way.
What is your experience?
Well, I've been a journalist for years.
I worked in the regional daily press, I worked in Le Monde group
Also. I have edited quite a few media for large groups.
Yes, there was Flint at one time.
I don't know if that's still the case.
Flint, it’s Flint for once, it’s really one that’s always the same.
It's still there, it's the box which is called generation Today, therefore, Flint is
no, it's a machine learning start-up.
So who has been doing machine learning since 2017 with a background in Machine
learning, can you explain in two words?
Machine learning, in fact, if you are interested in AI, you need to know what
word because it's called machine learning.
This is basically the technology behind the training of what we call
language models. So who are the models here you have inside the
platforms like GPT chat.
Alright. Um and so it's this duo in fact that makes it difficult for me to speak
of something. There is so much hype, I wouldn't even say a lie actually but
false information circulating around AI.
as much in the hyper optimism as in the hyper pessimism that in fact we need to show
really what is the state of the art in fact then how is it useful to me too and to have
maybe dig a little deeper into the topics like you do in your newsletter.
Yeah. I always say critical and pragmatic thinking.
Pragmatic is actually there is what can I really really do?
So I only share things that I have been able to do that have been helpful to me.
And then critical thinking is, I take a step back, what are we talking about, what is
the technology behind what do we mean by and every time I try to explain
how do these DI models also work so that we always have this understanding
behind. There's nothing magical about it.
Overall, artificial intelligence is a toolbox in which you have
a brain which is the language model a platform different tools, disconnectors
and everything. You put that together and it gives you something that generally allows you to do
an action that normally could be done by a human.
But it doesn't necessarily work from start to finish.
There are a lot of errors.
You often have to put a human in the loop.
Finally, it is all this complexity that we embark on something which is
in any case what I think pleases our readers is that it's always me I say
still that in fact uh the acceleration of AI technology and even
geopolitics today is scary and I think that the best response to the
fear is curiosity. Um and so we are a newsletter which is animated
through curiosity. So I won't talk about optimism, I'm curious.
I'm interested to see what we can do.
I'm interested to see what we can, you are quite balanced in what you say.
Um I feel like you're you're really balanced.
It's true that there are really two worlds that are separating in a way that
quite important. I found on the AI ​​community.
There are the antis. It's not the antis but it's people who tell us here we are
we're going towards GI so the famous super intelligence or artificial intelligence
general following who speaks.
And that's problematic because it could really wreck our current world
societal level, at the level of many things.
And then there are the others who are a bit techno ba, I want to say, people
who pray to God Elon or God Samaltman and who for whom technology
will solve all the problems while we know in fact the two positions are a small
A little biased, I feel.
Yeah. And then you have to understand that I have nothing against billionaires,
but finally when we become a billionaire, we disconnect a little from reality
anyway also eh so uh and then behind also it's technooptimistic, it
we must not forget, there is also a somewhat transhumanist approach, even when we
says cat GPT is smarter than me for example, there is this idea that ultimately
our brain is a little incomplete, that's the whole transhumanist philosophy and that
AI will come uh well uh improve humans, replace us because it will precisely be
perfect and we are imperfect.
And I think that this talk of imperfection concerning the human brain is
have little knowledge of neuroscience.
The brain is imperfect because it needs to learn and we are machines
to actually learn somewhere.
I perhaps shouldn't have said machine, but that somewhere we are not
machines precisely, we are biological machines.
But by saying that ultimately we are only imperfect computers, I think
that it's not knowing philosophy well, not knowing science well, and that's all it takes
a speech according to who actually delights all the people who master this technology
there because somewhere it allows them to say to themselves well the future of the world is between
our hands. That's it. And to raise and raise tens or hundreds of billions
euros each year. So.
and then and with a philosophy that goes even further because all these people when
you look at uh the philosophy that animated some of these actors in Silicone
Vallée, they all studied philosophy, they are interested in politics and
somewhere the idea of ​​saying to yourself well in fact you have to know the actors
from Silicone Valley are hackers.
And when we say hackers, you are capable of hacking society and why not hacking
the system and why not hack democracy.
And what do we replace democracy with?
crazy example, I don't know if you've heard of this, but tech giants
in San Francisco who wanted to create an artificial island opposite California at 2
or only 3 km, almost visible from the beach to no longer have American rules
on technology. I don't know if we realize the madness of Yes, it's madness
of Peter but of a kind of freedom of the absolute individual but anyway, the freedom
when you're a billionaire, it's okay, you're free.
And my mother always said “Your freedom ends where everyone else’s begins.” Yes,
That's an old saying. It's an old saying but she told me it all the time.
It's true, I quite agree.
Okay, fine. Uh general, when you have more money, you have more freedom, eh.
So when you say my freedom ends where others' freedom begins, if the other has a lot
less money and much less connection, there are still imbalances
which is created. In any case, what I mean is that this technooptimism he has he has
roots. It's interesting to understand this because today these people who had
a lot of money now have a lot of power especially with AI and a capacity
to transform the world which is not innocent and today enters into one which is
also a geopolitical war.
So they are also supported by the States and therefore this mixture, I actually find
is quite dangerous. That's what fundamentally scares me more than what I
I wouldn't say delusion but belief in super intelligence.
I'm not saying that we'll get there, that we won't get there, but I think that the
dangers the more immediate risks are precisely linked to this kind of new
politics which is in the process of a new world order which is in the process of being organized and
where AI is at the heart of most tensions.
Yeah. Very interesting. Very interesting.
Well yes. Yes. There is a big debate currently on this.
I can actually see it. There are several worlds being created.
There are people who are completely outside of all that.
Besides, that's the majority of people in reality, eh.
Me, when I hear around me, yeah but everyone has gone to Clos, everyone
everyone did this, everyone did that, everyone tested open closed.
It makes me laugh because not everyone, your microcosm, a few people
have these tools and use them every day.
When we look at the figures we are very far from the cl I specify for those who who
have not understood who is the autonomous agent called autonomous agent and Claude therefore who
is rather Claude code which is often used because it allows both coding
and to do a lot of things in a semi-autonomous way, everything that we do, everything that is
linked autonomous in fact today eh which fits precisely on the on the way to of
tomorrow of this super intelligence which will do everything to our That's it.
Okay then, Benoît, let’s be pragmatic.
I think you're at least my age.
Um, I know it for real but you shouldn't say it.
Not even not even. So for me, you saw like me all the waves passing around
of the Internet. So I imagine there is the web, even the Minitel probably.
Very nice tool indeed.
You should know that at the time France was at the technological forefront at the time of
Minitel. We were the only ones who could book a train ticket online though
before the internet. Uh suddenly, you have seen all these developments uh Minitel, web, uh e-commerce,
social networks, maybe crypto too of course and now LIA of course.
In your opinion, why despite all these new technologies that are constantly arriving
and at a speed which for me is more and more delirious very clearly, uh why
In your opinion, the newsletter format is always a format that is also qualitative, interesting,
efficient and good for your personal community?
I think that obviously all these revolutions bring disruptions as they say,
a lot of change so it’s going very quickly, it’s accelerating.
And in fact in these very changing environments, I think that we will favor
robustness. Hm hmm. And email is a pretty robust technology, first of all, it's
a little bit at the origin, she she is she was born with the internet uh initially, everyone
uses it so it’s still something important.
She's not that intrusive even though she's quite intimate.
So it's a strange mix but in fact we don't receive a notification at
every time we receive an email.
In any case, if this happens to you, I recommend that you turn off the notifications instead.
Go check your emails uh at the times you want to go check them.
I go see them every 3 hours.
So, it annoys people when I don't respond to emails systematically, but I think
that it is basic hygiene to have.
But if we remove the notifications, in fact, we will see these emails, it remains intimate overall.
And so and that also takes up a whole culture that we have in society, finally in our
history, sorry, of humanity which is that of letters.
There were the newsletters that we distributed in the markets, it was the merchants,
the first media were handwritten newsletters
the merchants among themselves. This is also the most reliable information at the time.
So there is a notion of reliability which enters into our culture and a notion of me
find the epistolary side it's because I'm talking to you so I often kill you
besides people because there is a very intimate side we talk about person to person
person so it creates a link and in fact in this environment with social networks
which are attention-grabbing environments sometimes a bit of the relationship but
with relatively weak links, the newsletter does what it has a letter for
allows me to create much stronger bonds.
people can answer me.
We talk about it as a response elsewhere on the uh Ah a lot finally every time I
requests responses, we also have they have the possibility to leave comments.
So I get a lot more several do you use Substacle or a tool like that?
I use a newsletter platform called Beve which is a platform
American which is very uh and which constantly innovates each time which was made by
by the creators of Morning Brew which was a newsletter a huge newsletter which
had several million subscribers.
So these are people who create newsletters who created this platform for
people who do editorial newsletters too.
All right. Um and so I think this link question and also the question you know
letter uh in our history but I think it is in our imagination, in literature,
in the films uh you sit down, you open your letter and you take the time to
And the newsletter was made for us on Sunday and it's not a disposable newsletter.
People stop, have their coffee, open the newsletter.
They know they have it for a while.
We have 10 to 15 minutes of reading each time on the newsletters.
So it's also a moment for time uh which is quite rare in fact more and more
in you that we find in the podcast typically for example.
No, and that's what's close to podcasting, I think.
Besides the podcast which is still an old thing uh from the time of the iPod uh
which ultimately also held, which maintained itself and which even grew because precisely
it plays on the same levers which are the link, the long time and precisely a dimension
a little intimate in fact which we need in this absolute chaos today.
Yeah, actually, I have the impression that we are in a world that is becoming polarized,
that is to say that we really have increasingly rapid content which has been brought by
TikTok in particular and the other platforms that followed with content sometimes of
10 or 15 seconds. I don't know if you remember, we even had a tool called
Wine. It was 7 seconds of video.
Besides, it disappeared but I heard that there was a tech bridge that wanted
restart Vine. So to follow and you on the other side, you have the extra long formats.
Now, we have videos on YouTube that are 3 hours long and which are seen, really seen.
We have longer and longer newsletters, at least the ones that I follow more and more
longer. And it's true that sometimes, there is always this little one
problematic there and then we will really move on to something else about how to achieve a good
calculate the reading time in the case of the newsletter, the time of a podcast and I have
the impression that in fact it is more by feeling.
Do you confirm or do you have a more precise idea I think that's what we call
a little economy in fact the important thing is what type where is it
that it arrives at the moment when it is received by the person because there is the question
of place now what was not the case before under what conditions does it take place
on which on which device if it's on the phone or on the computer so in fact I hear
often say yes you have to make short content, make long content make
short videos make only video and not text in fact it means nothing in fact
and it's like the podcast we have moments in fact where we will read a text Moments,
we'll take a book from somewhere else too, sometimes we'll watch a podcast, sometimes
we're going to listen to it. I do, but I know that it’s done less and less in society
That. Yeah, we've been burying the book for years.
I think he's he's far from buried.
Uh yeah, but we can never pre No, the lead is an experience that has nothing to do with
even with the newsletter. It's a very special experience.
We also need to understand how our brain interacts with these formats.
But uh there is so I think there is there is the newsletter responds to a moment when we
is generally a little quiet.
Uh we have our newsletter, we take there is the fact of opening it, we take time
to think and I think that there are different rhythms in life and that everything is
not at the same level. Our brain is not at the same level of attention and then
obviously the long one is not good in itself in fact if you do the long boring one, if you do the
long without interest as the AI ​​is very capable of doing for example when you
put it in automatic mode, it can give you text toasts, that doesn't matter
interest. So she literally texts.
There you go, the long time is a moment that you take for your brain to take the
ch in any case this is what we are doing with Generation I to try to understand what
happens to take useful things which will be very practical that you will be able to
you also reproduce also.
And so it is a necessary moment in the current turmoil of calm, of reflection,
of taking a step back and also of the link that we will create with the reader.
Yeah. Then I think we really need it today because it's true as
you say the world is going crazy.
We won't talk about politics today, maybe a little bit about geopolitics, but
It’s true that we live in a completely crazy world.
Everything accelerates at one speed.
I remember when the web arrived, everything accelerated from my point of view.
I was young, I made my first website, I was 12 years old in my room.
But I had asked my mother for a computer.
At the time, it cost 10,000 francs, I remember the price.
For her, it was way too expensive.
She was alone, three children.
Finally, I'll let you imagine the difficulties she had.
she was an employee, eh, so a little extra salary.
In short, all that to say that at the time, I started there, uh I see
things speed up. E-commerce has also accelerated things, social networks
accelerated things, crypto accelerated things, NFTs accelerated, me
remember that NFTs, I said to myself but it's not possible, we are almost in time,
the long time is a day, you see.
Uh and now with AI, well I found something that is even faster than
the NFT. I say to myself, what's the next step?
Besides, to change a little bit, finally to evolve a little on the subject because we
has a lot to see today and I see that time is already passing very quickly.
For me generation AI, I feel that it is you who writes.
Maybe I'm wrong.
Maybe you worked very well on your agent, I do too so it's possible.
But in any case, there is a roof inside.
Now that I know you very well, it's really a big deal.
How do you manage to resist temptation?
If you resist it, maybe you'll tell me "I couldn't resist it."
How do you resist the temptation to let AI do everything?
See? And what is your red line if you have one?
What is your red line for automation and link usage?
I think this debate about writing with AI is a false debate.
and I believe that the real question first of all is to know what do you
story you have to tell, how can you tell it and in the end
Are you going to put your at the bottom of the page?
For me, it's do you assume that you are proud of what you have?
from a legal point of view, from an emotional point of view that you are going to create, message that you have that you
you passed on and so on.
And so uh Li it's a tool.
So I wouldn't say that it's necessarily a tool for writing.
Um, by the way, I spoke with Hervé Lotellier with whom I had done a challenge
in 2025. We each had to write a new me with the AI ​​and him by hand which is Hervé
Le Tellier for Herv Leier is the 2020 pre-competition who has written uh superb books.
Uh on what subject? Pardon ?
On what subject? Did he write?
He's a writer. It's literature he wrote he wrote about what for the price
competition ? Uh the anomaly.
Which is a kind of novel, a bit science fiction, a bit strange.
It looks like a TV series.
It's very funny. Um, I loved this book so I have a lot of respect for it.
writer and he told me but in fact so I was interested to see what we could
do with client in terms of writing and he told me yes well it's interesting but
My real pleasure is writing and yes in fact that’s a bit the case for me too but I
I think that it fits into the recipe the question of knowing how
of which I use the AI ​​to write the first thing that I search in in the AI
it's that they obviously surprise me in general they surprise me So that's the
issue. So the idea is how are we going to work with her in a way
so that she is able to offer me new things.
So the first thing she usually does often is I gather my thoughts, I
know roughly what I mean.
So I put this in a file.
Then often out loud I dictate what I think and so on, but sometimes I know
not sure where my ideas are going to go, how I'm going to articulate them and then he offers me
several joints possible.
I choose, I challenge et cetera.
Yeah, you trade with the AI ​​to get the best possible result in the end.
So. Afterwards, I have a way of structuring uh uh the entire context of my AI
so that she behaves in a way that surprises me.
Um afterwards, I worked a lot on writing, in particular this challenge that we had
do. So, we had to beat the pre-competition on short story writing.
So, we beat it which was interesting on a short story, not on a novel,
it's more complicated. Then afterwards, I did the exercise again where it is the new observer
who gave me this challenge.
We redid, we had to finish the unfinished book by Flobert Bouvert and Pécuché.
We had to finish the last chapter.
So and obviously everyone tells me it's easy to do flobert with AI.
Of course the AI ​​can in fact pastiche an author of being here is me what I wanted is
wake up the ghost of Flobert and see to what extent I could bluff a specialist
by Flobert. So that was it.
We made him read a Flobert specialist.
said the ghost of Flobert woke up.
Why anyway? Because I didn't try to pastiche a style.
I tried to understand how Flobert thought.
So we have You analyzed the way maybe excuse me you analyzed the way
Flobert thought, perhaps reflected on his way of working Yes, because in fact
the style is not what you see in the style of Flobert which is actually
which is very recognizable.
What is interesting is to know why he writes like that, what is the machine
behind. And I always think that the content conditions the form.
So the style is actually bullshit.
The style must in fact express the substance elsewhere.
So if you don't understand how someone works and if you yourself when you write,
you haven't thought about what you want to say, how you're going to articulate things,
We don't care about your style. So asking the AI ​​to copy your style makes no sense.
And besides, she's basically going to do something pastiche.
Yeah. It's going to look like it from afar.
Who will impress overall et cetera.
And so the idea was to think about how Flobert thought.
So there are a lot of things that have been described about him.
There are the famous letters to Lis Colé and LColé which are letters where he speaks
of his writing with this woman.
So letters that really say what not only what he thinks but also where
he writes in a much freer way than what he does in these novels.
And from there we analyzed and we have there is a lot of prompting work
behind work eh.
took several weeks to create this famous chapter which you can find elsewhere
in in one in one of the copies of the OPS and on the site also.
And all this to say that in fact when I work with AI, I often go
ask him to help me articulate my thoughts how could I
do them and then I have lots of vocabulary tools that I will use to
say hey uh checks the rational connection.
So what is the rational connection?
It's a technique, it's between two sentences, between two paragraphs that what
is a connection. Which allows the reader to clearly understand when you go from one point
at a point Z, to fully understand each connection between rational things.
You say, so the situation is like that but in fact it's not exactly
that's what you have to think about. In fact, this is the real problem.
Have you really made the connections well that allow readers to not be
be lost in everything you're talking about?
And then I do some work, so afterwards, I can ask him to write.
That gives a bit of a first idea, a first G.
And I have prompting techniques which sometimes mean that I get a quote,
sometimes it will have a kind of it will have a little a little intimate side,
a little funny. Sometimes he'll come up with punchlines that I wouldn't have thought of.
So here, I'm going to take them.
Um and then sometimes I write everything by hand, it doesn't really matter.
And sometimes I tinker, sometimes I take things he wrote, sometimes I
I actually make my own sauce.
And once again the important thing as a musician somewhere, I would say as well
Christopher Nolan when he talks about AI, he says "Well it's a tool so in fact we are
creator and we have a debate on the term tool for AI.
You know there is a big debate on this.
We will say that he is a collaborator rather than a tool.
You're right because it's not really a tool, it's more of a collaborator.
He is also a creative collaborator for you.
It's rather united. Ah yes, besides there may be one, that gives me
an idea for a question that I hadn't anticipated but for you maybe AI could be
creative? But the question makes no sense once again gen it's no but it's necessary
let it be answered when Okay.
But AI is not creative in itself.
So unless you consider that indeed for me it is creative.
Well, very good, but tell me why.
But because sometimes I am surprised by the results.
So that doesn't mean, be careful, maybe it's not the right vocabulary term
vocabulary level, but for me, it in any case has an air of creativity because
sometimes she surprises me and I'm like wait, but how did you connect these dots?
? You know, I'm a fan of a specific concept that was very good
documented by Steve Jobs, connecting the dots.
He explains in one of these interviews that I recommend to you all, we will put here
Besides, I hope you find it, it's at Stanford, I think.
There is something, there is a passage that is extraordinary in this thing.
He talks about connecting the do.
So he said, when I was young, I wanted to go to a calligraphy school.
calligraphy, you see the design of the letters literally for those who know
not. Okay. He tells his parents that.
His parents say “But what are you telling me?
Do you think you're going to find a job with that?" In addition to parents of Iranian origin
which are very square, you see.
No no but that doesn't work for you.
Yes but please, I really want to, you will see, it will be useful to me.
Blah blah. He attended calligraphy school for several months.
Nothing happens after that.
Afterwards, he goes into something completely different.
He becomes the Steve Jobs we all know.
And one day a computer arrives on his desk, a Mac of course and he
says "There is a problem. I find that the fonts of the equivalent of Word
at the time, I don't know what it's called anymore, the equivalent of your word processor
at the time which was very new, we were at the very beginning of Mintosch, he said there
the font doesn't work at all, it's disgusting.
I can't sell a product." He was in the level of detail he wanted
also that the font of his Mac is qualitative.
And so that's where he connected the dots.
And yes, his brain. Ah yes, but wait, I went to calligraphy school, I
know how to draw letters, I know how to create something beautiful and interesting.
That's why he says you shouldn't connect the dots in advance, you have to connect them
after the fact in fact. Exactly.
And uh and it's true moreover about the calligraphy, it was interesting because uh
I worked for a long time with a designer who told me that the best school
that it is made, it is first of all calligraphy because in fact uh we often say that
beginning was the verb eh.
Um, but besides, it’s a sentence that also goes very well on desire piloting.
eh, the words, the vocabulary.
Yes, tell us about this story.
You talked about it in one of your recent newsletters.
I would like you to talk to me again about Stat Gastad.
Ah the words we use.
but yes because then to come to creativity is Li creative or not
? I actually does L have anything to say?
I don't know. I think we can do experiments to try to see if there
has in relation to what she has what she has absorbed.
What did she say?
Once again AI does not think like us.
So it makes the uh complex prediction clearly of the best answer in relation
to the whole to the to his training obviously.
So what we call its internal knowledge, therefore a sort of compression whatever
apart I would say. way of talking about everything she's read.
Um even if the term is not completely adapted, but it's a bit like that.
So she doesn't have a database from which she draws.
Then, there is the context in what we are going to bring to her and from that, she will predict the
best answer. So tell her that she has something to express in fact no because
that it actually depends first on the internal knowledge and then also on the context
of the question that will have been asked.
So somewhere, there is always an influx.
So the question of pure creativity of AI, for the moment, I think we have not
still all the elements, although it is an artistically interesting subject to try
to question Li but it makes me laugh at people who ask the question to know
what he feels, well in fact he will answer you what you want you to answer him, you
see. finally let him answer you.
So in a way, I find it much more interesting to consider him as a collaborator.
We are going to say tool actually because it allows you to position yourself by
relation to new technologies and the creative takes advantage of them.
I don't know a single artist who is afraid of glia being creative, he doesn't care [ __ ]
He uses it, he doesn't use it, he misuses it, he diverts it.
That's it, he breaks it, he does what he wants with it.
So somewhere uh and so I would say that compared to that the real
I position myself as a human, what can I do with this machine
? She has plenty of limits.
The I have a lot of tickets.
For example, you ask Ali to make you a premium design, Claude will always make you
the novel capitals like that and then hop Because suddenly it's elegance, it creates
an emphasis. So it's nice, it's a school.
Except that in fact between the years 2000 and 2026 in fact everyone started
to do that so all the apps and so on and so as soon as you ask it to do a
general premium design without mentioning the I we have a global standardization which therefore
there is a real risk of crushing creativity you see with the so that's why
that I think that hybridization with humans interacts with me what I call la la
intentional friction with the AI ​​is that you don't let it do it like that all of a sudden
you will constantly be interacting with her in any case for certain tasks
Ugh, that's okay but
on the other hand on the tasks we will say creative productive in which you must
bringing value LIA is a collaborator who thinks differently from us.
So that’s his, that’s that’s also his interest which is rather complementary.
There are rules of collaboration to have in order not to involve interaction
too much our own biases or even the AI's own tickets.
And it's actually an art to learn how to work with AI and that's what I'm trying
me to explore on my own and pass on with the little that I have learned to my Benoît,
I have a question to ask you.
For you, is the audience a bit like the new currency?
You see, it's a bit like the new token first of all.
And secondly, do you think the audience is good for the rest?
That is to say, is it stronger than traditional marketing?
Is it stronger than advertising?
And how do you see things in relation to your audience who I know are very loyal
to your newsletter currently?
I think so I'm not a marketing expert so I'm speaking with these with a
little nuance and I speak from my experience and then my experience as a journalist that
for this reason I set up media where in fact I have always put the community
relationship with the audience at the heart in fact I come from the local press.
The local press is the story which is the rough draft of the local history which is told.
If there is no local press there is no common story.
In fact it is and is very underestimated the PQR.
Yes, because as soon as you remove the local press, particularly in the United States, in
fact, politics is polarizing again because suddenly, we no longer have an anchor
in fact about our own history and we come to speak in a very abstract way uh
of national problems while we have the link between people is created by a
common story that we tell each other.
This is to paraphrase Yuval Noa Harari, the historian.
And so the press is there for that.
So, I'm starting from the press because it's my it's my calligraphy somehow
leaves, if I dare say so. and the local press in particular, the creation of links with the community,
this is what allows it to be the strongest link in fact because we tell a story
together and I think that therefore that means that we must respect this community
there. Besides, there is a difference between audience and community, it's not the same
thing. The audience you're talking to, so you're on YouTube, you have 20,000 subscribers,
Well, you have an audience of 20,000, it's not a community.
Your community is when people start talking to each other. We're trying
to create so we for example we have 42000 as I speak to you 42000 33000 I believe
newsletter subscribers. FYI, you subscribe right away, it deserves 100,000
minimum. Um and we have a community, we have a community of 600 people on the group
WhatsApp, people who bought our training, who wanted to be part of the community
and which of them on the other hand interact constantly even I I hardly intervene
more and they exchange information, advice, they also know each other
them and so on. So for me, that's the community and the community moreover, it's
much stronger than the audience because there you really create a link in fact
which means that there is something that I really like to say about the community,
it's when you have people when you are attacked who come to defend you in your place.
That means that there is a bond that has been created that is much stronger.
I experienced it anyway.
Yes. And then uh but without having these ideas behind the
head, I would say somewhere for me marketing is being useful to people in
do. it's about being useful and making sure that but useful in the right way, it's about
fact is to ensure that what you offer them elevates them and when it elevates them
Well, in fact, first they know you, then they also raise you on their side.
It's of course it's a real exchange which ultimately everyone learns everything Exactly
and I I me what what bases my whole story and all the work that I have been doing since
that I am a local journalist until today my use of AI but there is a
actually clear consistency in this whole story.
I started with the local press, I did participatory media because I believed
to people's participation when it is supervised, when it is stimulated.
And I believe that AI is also a tool of emancipation because I think that every
person, whether we are here in Bali, whether we are in France, in a village, in a camp
refugee or at the top of the state, everyone has a story, everyone
has a story to tell and We end up dying in the end, but when we die, the
the only thing we're going to leave behind is a piece of history that will be transmitted to millions
of people, to 10 people, it doesn't matter.
d' I have to tell the story of my father, you spoke to us about that in Yes, I have
worked a lot on memories because memories and it allows everyone,
each person who has a story but who doesn't necessarily know how to tell it.
Can you remind us, excuse me for cutting you off, can you quickly remind us what
you made do with it, I think it was with your dad it seems to me.
Yes. Well, starting from the principle that my father is he is a surgeon, he was a researcher
so a lot to convey about his vision of beauty because he worked a lot
on the maxilofacial, aesthetics and so on.
So he looked into this question a lot and then even with his hands somewhere he
was confronted with the question of beauty.
Um at the same time, he also has a personal story, a love story with my
mother uh and stories of friendship too, failures, uh a lot
of things, a whole life story.
say that interests who then it will interest because yes we say there are 8 billion
of people everyone I often hear that in the Parisian elite all
everyone doesn't have something interesting to say well if everyone has something interesting to say
say just go see them and I have a little message from elsewhere to the Parisian elites
uh well Parisian elite like elite everywhere will not tell you what people think of you but
there we have examples on the call no but I have nothing against the elites no I have I have
I have I have I have nothing against the elites for me it's a it's a social environment like
another simply you have to coexist with the others it's Yeah.
So. And don't look at the water people.
Afterwards, I think we need intellectuals, we need artists, we need
stars, we need influencers, we need workers, we need people who have
Otherwise, society will not run properly if we don't have all of these.
And so for me, every time I went to see people where they were, it could be
anyone. I always had a story to come out with.
Obviously, we have to go and extract the story.
It's like going fishing.
Um, you have a very beautiful story with Catherine and Philippe.
Yes, because well this story which was they had the story, it carries it on You
can quickly explain to our Yes.
So, Catherine Philippe, it's a couple of donations really made, we really made
digressions we don't I didn't end up on my father by the way but ok.
So uh so Philippe, it’s an absolutely extraordinary story since they are
They came to Bali not long ago.
These are a couple who were more executives who work at Pôle Emploi
Besides. So he was HR director, he was uh I think DSI if I'm not mistaken and
so rather high positions and at 60 they decided to give up everything.
She decided to take her CAP in pastry.
She won the competition for the best chocolate mousse in Paris somewhere
to somehow fulfill the dream of her son who said "But mom, your foam
chocolate was incredible." He actually called her chocolate mom.
Uh and you should come and sell it in Japan because they don't know it
that in Japan. So they left their job in Japan.
Instead of retiring, they packed their lives into three suitcases.
They went to live in Japan.
They were a hit there.
They were selling 400 pots of moss a day by the end in large Japanese luxury trunks.
But they couldn't go any further because no one trusted them because they
are too old. Say yes but you are too old.
How will the brand continue if you die at 60?
Are you going to die at 70 or 80?
Well, these financiers lacked a lot of imagination.
They came back to France to go up and develop that in Normandy which
is the which is their country which is their their country it is a country Normandy almost
we can say that their region of origin still has no financier when in fact enormous
success uh the foam is obviously excellent but TF1 brut are reporting they
were seen by millions of people and finally they ended up finding a
an investment when they were on the verge of bankruptcy an investor who worked
in the restaurant business and moreover they signed when they were in Bali, we
was in they made a pop store there it's in progress there I think and so they come
to therefore relaunch the brand so it is a real rebirth on the continuation of
ventured here. Yeah, her name is Catherine Bréard so you can go and see.
Incredible story. Incredible story.
This woman is extraordinary and thank you Benom.
Yes, because the message is that in fact whatever your age, first of all you have a story
to tell, you have something to do, you can change your life, you can continue your
dream even at 60 years old even when no one believes in it.
And she always says if you want to get the next door there, you have to push
the first. You have to push all the time, you have to open doors all the time.
And above all she has an energy, she has a joy of life, she has a kindness and I
I believe in the power of kindness.
Uh and uh and I find them to be extremely inspiring people.
Besides, as soon as people meet her, everyone starts to cry, eh.
So uh joy eh, joy and also cry when he eats because she is when
even very good and you are very because the foam carries its work Can you
end up on your father? How did you set it up?
We're going to get into AI a little.
We're going to come back to AI anyway, it's important.
How did you use AI to help your father tell his story?
? you told us about it in the newsletter, but I would like you to tell me today
in podcast for those who have not read and are not yet absolute fans of Benoît Raphaël.
What did you put in place for your father and what were the results?
obtained today? And because once again, my father has lots of things to say
but like many people, he either doesn't have the time or he doesn't necessarily have the words.
So he has already written quite complicated scientific books.
he wrote, he released two books but hey here's telling his story then he
you have to extract all of that.
So in fact that somewhere is where artificial intelligence can help us
when it is well managed uh to allow everyone to tell their story and
this is where I find that it is still an extraordinary tool of emancipation
if only for families.
Uh, my mom, I told you I want to do I want to do this for my father.
He has incredible stories.
He was a paratrooper. Can you imagine?
Of course. Because when a person, me, my mom, died at the beginning of the year
and my reflex was to make a book or to make a book.
So we made a book with parts of the speeches and what we remembered from the photos.
then all his paintings his story was his paintings but this book I wanted
make it look good so people can put it in their bookshelves.
And for me the fact that people put the book in the library meant
that she continues to live because I don't believe in life after death.
I'm not saying it doesn't exist, I don't believe it.
So I don't have any proof, I don't know.
So in any case at least the story continues and it is this trace that we will leave.
So for me the story of each person is important for the dignity of each person and for
living together.
We need our shared stories.
So how did you actually work?
That was the bottom line but how did I work on it?
Well in fact quite simply I installed it so what they call me I call a
Personal AI is that it's a it's instead of being on a chatbot you're going to work
with an AI agent who will work on your files in your computer because you have to
that the AI ​​which accesses your computer your files your Here you open a folder in
your computer that you call workspace my book whatever you want.
Um, you're going to work with Claude Code on this because Claude Code is an agent
which but in fact the the the code is files in fact and therefore CL is very good for
manage files. Files are text and a program is knowledge
somewhere eh. Are files with a certain number of elements.
So it works the same way.
So we realized very quickly and now everyone obviously notices it
but we realized a year ago that the code was very good for precisely
manage knowledge.
So you have your folder in which you are going to put your files.
So, that's going to be what I did with my father, we created a material folder
uh divided by chapter roughly the things he was going to tell, so his story
with my mother, her professional history, her childhood, her friendships, aviation, everything
what he has, everything that matters in life and so on.
And so once we have the chapters, he simply has to fill in the material then
then we have another folder in which there are the chapters and there we will begin
to write little by little from this material.
And so he simply and well so excuse me for cutting you off.
First of all, the first step is the collection of data, I want to say.
And then you move on to the second step of writing.
That's it. Yes because in fact when you write using AI uh the goal again
time it's not that the AI ​​necessarily writes for you and that you use it, you use it
you are a collaborator you will use when you need it.
So you can also use it to write to make a draft to help you
to write better. Well, not much of course.
And therefore the way of working on writing, after having done many theses since
quite a few years, I find that the best method today is when
even to structure what you are going to do, even if it's not always it's it's not always
what everyone wants to do, but at least it allows the AI ​​to know where it is
go. So, you give a framework, you make a plan in general and then you work
chapter by Why? because little by little in fact all your all your files are going
accumulate. So this will create a context when the AI ​​comes to work in your file,
it will have all the context, the plan, what has already been written et cetera.
So that will help him And then you collect everything in what I call a document
of work. So you put all the data, the references that you have et cetera and then
afterwards you always do a part with the voice also that you will bring to the moment when you are going
to write. And this is your texture in fact.
Yes, because we also say, you tell me if I'm wrong, but we also say that when
we talk, there are things we say that we wouldn't have said in writing because we apparently
from what I've read, when we write, we put barriers on ourselves that we don't put on ourselves when
we talk. Is that true?
Well yes, because when you write, you are already formulating something.
So in fact, there you go, that’s why there is psychoanalysis anyway, you’re talking about
and and often you speak freely like that to let the You say more things in
speaking than writing. Finally, you have Yes, there you go.
you have less barriers.
So Freud talks about the super ego which creates this barrier there uh but in the same way
that when you write, it's not the same.
When you write by hand, it's not the same.
So your brain doesn't work the same way.
So you have to test all these writing methods.
You should know that Freida Mcfadon who wrote The Housekeeper and Bestella
absolute, we like it, we don't like it, we think she wrote Cunia.
I don't think so because it's not that easy to reproduce what she
do. The way she writes is that she walks and she talks.
What is she talking to? It's by dictaphone.
And so and that's why when you read these books, there's uh there's that you
you have the impression that it is a woman who is speaking.
It's very much talked about in fact somewhere.
Exactly. It's very spoken.
She has reactions like that.
Sometimes the character is spoken to and she reacts like that, which is still annoying.
And as a result it gives a very style And so I find this technique interesting but
On the other hand, behind her she has everything prepared.
So the whole plan in fact is prepared and in fact his work on the way, he will come and give,
he will come and bring life.
So what I do is that my father, I created a little application for him that
I called Steno. So I have coded vibe, we say coded vibe, it's when you code without having
coded with AI. I used Lovable to do this by the way.
And suddenly, he presses a button, he speaks.
There is a there is a little pr moreover which means that we will try not to
fool about named entities, it can put its own dictionary et cetera.
So it gives it a result which will then send uh in code and code will then
little by little distributing the right information in the right place.
Once you have the material.
So this allows it to enrich the material, bring a little granularity and
then after that you can work chapter by chapter from that.
So it's a system where the AI ​​will ask you questions.
Uh you're going to answer it, it's better to answer the voice.
I think it's much better in any case for his memoirs.
You have you're going to have it's super easy for him Yeah.
Then he could do some research.
It’s because my father can talk about something and then tell Claudiens about it.
I was telling you about my father was a surgeon so he created the first service of
Max Fa in Grenoble. So what was the story of Grenoble?
So he has memories at a given moment there is a kind of struggle between Lyon
and Grenoble because Lyon didn't want Grenoble to have a faculty then and my father told me
a story it happened in such a way and so on I'm you sure I well I'm more
really sure. So we asked Claude what.
He was going to do a search on the internet.
Well yes indeed he was right.
It happened on this date and so on.
and actually see if see if he remembers something that really existed because
that you know that there is also a concept, I don't know if you had heard of it
there are certain memories that we literally invent and we no longer know right from wrong
by our brain works a bit like GPT eh in fact we constantly reconstruct
our memory, that's why it's interesting to use
AI to store our ideas, our memory and so on, the famous files somewhere
MD that can be used on text files MD idea that can be used on the cloud in particular
which allow you to store data a little.
By the way, a quick point on that, do you have any context problems?
sometimes about your father's project?
Doesn't the AI ​​have too many files?
So, do you have to do some sort of compression of these files?
No, because in fact what you need to understand is that when you work on your
workspace with all your folders in which there are files, Claude
code when it arrives the MR when it arrives on code he when you create you have a program
of code, you have lots of folders, lots of files, that’s a lot of tokens so
of words eh, he's not going to read everything.
Ah no so there is Fortunately otherwise no and and besides there is there is not
of infinite memory. So they have no memory, I recall it once again to
those who believe that they have a memory.
Wait, it's marked memory.
But yes, it's bullshit.
In fact, I's have no memory.
Memories are files.
So there are files.
So even though JPT when it tells you it has memory, it has a file in which
he stocks things more or less well elsewhere.
It can be accessed elsewhere and he accesses it at certain times.
So code, it's the same thing when you enter a workspace.
So it's like an office like here.
So. And in fact, well that's my AI And she comes in, she works with me on
folders that are configured.
Excuse me, I moved your I moved Michael Jackson.
I'm sorry man. Sorry Réy.
Come on, keep going, keep going.
I hit the star. So uh there you go and so your workspace is
like a file. You're going to put you're going to have your AI work with you on a
dedicated space. So you don't include it in all your files.
This is a file that is specially made for him.
As if you bring Nia into a room and you tell her, so there are these files
there. In these folders there are files.
These are the procedures. You also give him skills with processes and then in
on each file, that's where it's important, you put a postit where you tell him
this is what this folder contains, this is what you can do in it.
Otherwise, obviously when your intern or your junior collaborator arrives in
your office, your workspace, open everything every time you come home because it
comes in every time, it comes in brand new eh.
he has no memory he's going back, he's going to have to beat himself even if he goes very quickly he's going
he has to type all the files, it's impossible besides that's what's required
too much would require too much calculation of yes then that would create noise so it serves to
nothing so the idea is to have a small document that we call the cloudm when we use
cloud code or the agentmd when using other agents of other ancient images like
codex for example and in this case he will read this file there he knows it has a map
what is the folder structure when it goes to what time sometimes there are
files that he absolutely must see at the start so you structure your memory
in the therefore there is a lot of work of preparation and structure in fact all the work
and that's why it's not the AI ​​that writes, it's firstly how you constitute your
folder how do you how do you create your files how do you create the cartography
the path that the AI ​​will take how it will it will find its way so it must be necessary
demonstrate what Amanda Asquel who is the philosopher who is at the origin of the
CL Claude's personality calls for empathy towards machines.
That is to say in fact when you work with AI, you have to be empathetic in the sense
you have to understand what she can do, how she thinks, how she thinks,
how she works and put her in place.
You're facing a blind person, you're doing things in Braille, you see.
Um well it's the same way when you are faced with AI which is one which is neurodivergent
well she thinks differently.
So you're going to put in place the files, the right guides, the right lines
guidelines to help him work.
So for example, you were talking about Mark the Markdown format, it's a text file format
in fact but which makes it possible to prioritize the text which can be read by AI as well as by
humans. The difference in the code in fact if you spoke in ALIA code, it would be a lot
better. She understands code better than Yeah.
But this format is good for both.
So it's cool. So. And so it's a way of showing empathy, of telling you we
work together, so I will adapt to your way of working and uh in a way to
so that it is as effective as possible.
Exactly. You tell us in a recent newsletter that the vocabulary is a bit
the new code. You're going to tell us a little about it earlier but quickly, but
do you think that code schools should suddenly be replaced by
faculties of literature or faculties of philosophy for example?
That's a real question.
I believe it was André Skarpati who said that the new code was English because
that he is American so obviously André Skarpati is one of the founders of Pen who
is doing a lot of popularization today.
He's someone I recommend you follow, much more interesting than
Samman on social networks.
Well he's an engineer so basically and uh and so uh it's a real question
because first of all the code is still the language of AI in fact eh because
that in fact they learned about language but also about code.
The advantage with code is that it is a very structured language.
Second advantage with the code is that we train the I for and therefore what we call
a training station. We will see if the answers are correct or not and we will
allow them to be corrected, eh.
This is how we improve their behavior.
In training, there is in particular what is called reinforcement learning.
However, reinforcement learning works very well when we have zero or
1. So it works or it doesn't work.
The code either works or it doesn't.
Uh, here's a bau de l'air poem, it works, it doesn't work, but it actually depends on you.
You see a lawyer, it’s the same.
There are no completely objective criteria.
Exactly. So it's much easier to train.
Moreover, the progress of the I on the code will go exponentially.
We have confidence that they will surpass humans.
They will already start to surpass him and even the best humans very quickly.
uh and even on fairly complex tasks which is less the case for the rest because we
is less successful in training them because we are working on tasks that are subjective.
So it's difficult to say it's good, it's not good unless you introduce tickets.
So that's why it's so I would say that speaking the code is not bad because in
done when you speak code with a you also speak you speak to him much better.
So I won't go so far as to say that we no longer need code because I think we need
also know how to speak their language.
So what will happen in the I don't know on the other hand to pilot them for
orchestrate them whether you are a coder or not a coder obviously code with AI you code better
with AI when you are a coder because in fact you are an expert in your Because you see the
errors, you analyze. Besides, I have an example later that I will share with you
on Pikachu. that I vibe code well in fact I vibe code but uh there you go uh there you go
I'm wearing two slippers instead of hands.
But on the other hand, words are precisely my net and my tools in
facts that will allow me to work and why vocabulary is important
realizes that well first of all they react enormously to each word
they only react to the words.
Yes. Give us your two examples of words there that you shared in say for example make me
an analysis. So first of all it's going to be the feminalysis analysis, that says it all.
Well uh so uh then Claude Claude is going to give you a critical analysis because he criticizes
cat GPT will perhaps do a it's not a synthesis not the same as the analysis already
and if you ask to do a guestalt analysis for example al what does that mean
say guestalt then analyze guestal I think that this word means nothing but it is
quite a guestal means something.
the combination of the two words, sorry, means nothing.
Well, basically, I don't think there are any guestal terms, it's up to
both a German term and at the same time a school of psychology.
All right. which allows us to see the whole in the multitude therefore allows us to bring out
which will unite a little bit.
We will we will bring together what is simple ultimately gives everything is relative but this simple
word rather gives a lot of context and information to the AI ​​to do your analysis.
That's because you have to understand before that how language models work.
So once again a language model when it reads millions of texts
in all of them and then he's going to uh process them.
So it will transform that into a connection between words.
So connections between words, concepts and so on.
So he has no knowledge that is when I tell him what is a guestal analysis
when I tell him for example what the capital of Paris is.
the AI ​​does not have the capital of Paris.
What is the capital of France, sorry which is Paris, excuse me for my broken tongue.
I am eh. So when you tell him what the capital of France is, there is no
file with a small drawer in which there is a capital sheet of France, it is
Paris. In fact, the AI ​​does not know that the capital of France is Parise.
She's going to No, she's not going to look at all.
It will reconstruct the information in relation to what will come back into this data.
It turns out that overall uh France capital Paris always comes back together.
So in fact it has a very strong assurance that 99.9% of being s but it works for everything
the rest too.
Which means that when she answers you, she answers in relation to probability
the strongest. This is why sometimes we have hallucinations, the famous hallucinations.
because they reconstruct the information.
But like us, we reconstruct the information.
At home, we call it confulation.
At Lisè, we call it hallucinations.
It's almost the same phenomenon.
We fill the holes. All right.
Humans do the same. That is to say that Yes, when you have an example well in fact, typically
when you uh when you had a trauma in childhood, you more or less forgot it.
In fact, you have holes in your life.
As a result, your brain will fill in the gaps.
Um and the neuroscientists explain to you that in all your memories anyway,
your way if you have information in which you are missing elements because the brain
needs stability somewhere.
So. So you're going to you're going to smooth fill the holes.
The same way that there is less your the less you are clear, the less the data on which
trained are strong. So the probabilities are low.
The more holes there are in his knowledge, the more holes there are in your
your more it will tend to fill the holes.
So that's where she's going she's going to do she's going to hallucinate making mistakes.
I understand. Um and so the words why so what we need to understand is
that it’s all about connections.
So when you tell him do an analysis well you can imagine like that you have the word analysis
then like that you have lots of connections which will be made with known concepts.
analysis psychoanalysis analysis so maybe engineering medical analysis full of words
like that and then if you add gestal like German psychology so then that
is going to do things and therefore above all it is going to open doors imagine that
it's a path that you actually open when you talk with a bit like for Catherine
just now you have to open the first door it's the first door it's like a tree
in fact so you open you open a branch there is a door on the branch you take
this branch there and there there are new new branches which will appear the word
will allow you to open up news If you want to have a quality analysis that allows you
to have a somewhat high vision uh what can I tell you roughly in all these testimonies,
what is it what is it what is it what unites all these messages for example
? you could say tell me what unites for these ages but if you say give me an analysis
guestalt in fact it will open all these all the literature around guestal of psychology
all the literature around analysis and in fact you open doors that you would not have
not open if you had not used this that's what I call calling on knowledge
hidden from her in fact when she answers you she always answers on the surface underneath you
as an iceberg in fact she has quite incredible knowledge but everything is
hidden by connections.
And if you are not going to open the first door which is a word, who will open a second
door which is a word et cetera, but now I like you because you are telling me
that we are returning to the peak, I want to say, of general culture,
to know how to work with words, to try to understand, to try to learn
things. Finally, then it's the revenge of the literary people eh somewhere I
I would say because in fact the tools are words.
To manage AI today, you have to be clear, you have to be precise and above all you
realizes that to get the right skills from LIA for
have really amazing, really different, really precise results, well
you need to know how to find the right words and therefore knowledge of the vocabulary.
And once again I say to myself or but it's an intellectual thing.
No, that's okay, don't see the word as an intellectual thing.
We have to stop these stories.
It's actually the word it's a tool it's a tool that allows you to have the right
reaction in a language model because the language model makes connections
between the words. That's his way of thinking.
So if you want to work with him, your tools are words.
All right. So, you were also talking about a concept that I really liked, uh the mode
drunk. Um, so that has nothing to do with alcohol, eh, I'm clarifying, I hope.
But it's interesting, you're going to develop us.
The question is why according to you, perfection, the relative perfection of intelligence
artificial is its biggest fault?
And the second question, how do we go about reinjecting a little entropy and
of errors perhaps to have more interesting results and get out of the famous
standard that you were talking about earlier?
So, I'm going to go a little outside of my area of ​​expertise, which is I'm a journalist,
my specialty is news.
But to talk about Shannon, but that m Shannon, it's information theory.
So it’s still connected with my job, but in a very different way because
that it's we're more in an area of ​​What does Shannon say?
This is so that information is reminded me who is Al Claude Shannon who is a
which is an Okay. THANKS.
which is one of the pairs of cybernetics of all the tourists
information and therefore also artificial intelligence.
So for information to be interesting, it must have a form of entropy.
That is to say that in fact it must create a surprise.
Typically take an example al making an analogy with him he was not talking about
language, he was talking about mathematics but it's the same thing.
Uh in any case we can also apply it uh when you say uh something to
when are you going to say something that will create information that will create a surprise
? you say for example yes then at the moment on AI it is a geopolitical issue et cetera
for me it doesn't give me any information so I won't remember it if you tell me
say but in fact what we don't know about that is that actually uh it is
It's not China that's winning, it's India.
I'll tell you anything.
It's not quite anything.
We have a video in preparation on this.
So you see I completely captured your Ah.
So that's the question of surprise.
So important information is information that creates surprise.
This is also the information that we will remember.
So it's the antibouhi the antibullshit somewhere.
I have to deliver it afterward.
When you make an announcement like that, you have to send something heavy behind the problem
of AI, it is when it is trained uh in fact therefore the principle of the machine
learning and deep learning, so deep networks are
that in fact when it is going to be trained on a demo, it will then have to predict
she will verify by making a prediction.
She must always try to have as few surprises as possible because that
That's basically it's necessary that basically she's going to make a prediction and if her prediction
is 90% that the answer is cat and the answer is cat little surprise surprise
by 10% I finally give you some maths like dad with my own mat level
what I understood what my partner explained to me he get fucked no no because
no because I'm doing it again I think that I'm telling the path that I have
traveled and uh and uh and I popularize with what I
what I know but I think a lot with my partner who is an engineer,
He knows that a little better than me.
But in fact on the other hand if he predicted 10% cat and I say cat, I [ __ ]
surprise, big level of surprise.
So what they try to do during training is to reduce to
maximum surprise. And yes because they want they want that in general the answer
is good for the end user a good prediction.
That's it. So what we call works and therefore from there therefore necessarily the
IAS are naturally trained to do somewhere
to be as least surprised to be as least surprised as possible.
So when you ask them to write a text, the text is often
quite bullshit, quite bullshit, very corporeal in a particular style, therefore a lot
pastiche too, it annoys us but precisely because they don't have this surprise
there. So the best way to create surprise is to use
the vocabulary to seek out more unexpected connections, a little
more buried, we will say somewhere.
If we can talk about depth, it's not exactly that, but it's a bit like that.
Um and so obviously there, we're already going to inject the surprise because we're going to him we're going to him
make it go beyond. You actually allow him, you open doors for him too, it will stay
always the prediction. It always remains prediction, the surprise that we injected
in a in a system which is not surprising, we will say somewhere.
in his own place or he won't go crazy either.
That's it, isn't it? And then and there we are, so we're going to stay in a system with almost no
no surprise but there are a lot of interpolations that we can do with all that
and therefore have things that surprise us in everything she has learned but with
this limit that overall it is a machine to limit surprise it is a machine
quite uh quite smooth in one way or another.
Yeah. By essence ultimately by training.
Then afterwards, don't forget that there is also post-training with alignment
which is done to it by humans who will smooth things even more.
Quickly explain alignment to our It's a practice.
So alignment is making sure that the robot or machine does what you do to it.
requests. For example, you have a self-driving car.
So if she's completely autonomous, you say, "I'm going to Paris." But no, I'm going
go to Lyon. It's a bit boring, you see.
So if she decides to go to Lyon because she thinks it's better.
So those are the questions, we resolve them through alignment.
Um it's obviously also avoiding her uh and preventing her from making a bomb when
he has to make a bomb.
So there are also global security rules.
So working on alignment is key in fact.
There is a big topic on this uh in the scientific and entrepreneurial community
uh AI currently.
Yes. Then there are the famous three laws of robotics by Isaac Kazimov eh.
So. So that's what the alignment is.
This is the basics of alignment.
Remember, do you know, do you remember the three laws or not?
I'm going to try you give because you're the first no the first I remember it
robot must never take any action against humans.
There you go, this is the first.
I will let you say the rest in the comments.
It's a shame we don't know that anymore.
Normally it's a basic but that's life.
Sometimes we forget things but yeah actually I have the impression that we need exactly
the same for AI. Do you confirm?
We need Azimov's laws for artificial intelligence.
Yes but we already have them in So No but that's what we call No but apparently
people disagree.
No, there is no universal law if you want like Deazimov or actually
you must not kill a human, you must not harm a machine unless a human
asks you, you must not do any harm to knock.
There are all these three rules that are there.
But what I mean is that the most important thing is the question of alignment,
it's uh to ensure that the machine responds to what we ask of it in such a way that it
either uh by uh by itself.
It goes a little further than that today.
There are questions of security, there are also enormous questions which make
so that the machine is not going to lie to you for example, not having a strategy
to get around what you're asking of him.
because we must not forget that these machines have been trained on the way of thinking
humans. So in fact, they will also embrace these biases and may have
falsely human behaviors, in imitation of humans which will push them to lie
to have for to succeed in their strategy to not be cut off.
For example, there is a classic test, we offer the human to we tell the AI ​​that it
is going to be cut and we watch how she reacts and sometimes they have strategies
of lies to avoid threats also.
So that's all the work there on the other hand of what we call red team uh which
is going to be to control the the so I think that the alignment is it's the whole it's
this set of things and we're going to add something to it and that's where Amanda Skel who
is therefore the person who at tropic tropic it is they who worked the best
the personality so the personality is those who created clone for this here it is
alignment in the sense of the experience that you are going to have with the experience that
you're going to do what you ask obviously you're going to have a good
experience but above all we must never forget what Daria Modi said quite a while ago
of time but he continues to boss it's key Dario Modi who is the entropic boss
who said that social networks captured in intron do a little harm to our intelligence
in any case when we have excessive use its objective is that with in fact we are
rather improved that an exchange with clone is never an attention grabber perhaps
not a capture of the relationship even if it is indeed a business on which
the more and more I and you come out more intelligent and Amandasquel works
so that the AI ​​has enough friction so it can possibly contradict you
uh and in such a way that you might be able to stop the conversation
and not to restart. Claude is the only one today who says to me “Well, it’s
good session." Um while Chat GPT still but do you want me to
do you something extra?
You see, you constantly maintain the relationship and so that's what we call
to take up the philosophy of Ivanilic who spoke of the user-friendly machine, the
user-friendly technology. What is user-friendly technology?
It's a technology that doesn't just take, it also gives you, it increases you,
it improves you. And so friendly AI for me is also a departure from alignment.
make sure that she doesn't take too much from you, she gives you more
than what she takes from you. And I think it's in the debates about the alignment
and on AI today, it's a central point that we don't talk about much
Besides, we don't talk enough, it's to what extent the technology is nor bad
nor good in itself. It is not neutral either, we know that very well.
But on the other hand, to what extent is this the judgment we must have, to what extent
Does it give me anything compared to what it takes from me?
Because she always takes something from you?
Ah, that’s clear. We move to a slightly different moment in the show.
Benoît so I hope you will play the game.
Now it's you who will go into journalist mode a little bit for a few
minutes and I will answer your questions.
We're going to talk about a subject. There you go, I told you about it at the start of the video, I don't know
if we can see clearly there. Hop. Well, you will see at worst I will send I will send cards
Pokémon. So these are very specific, Indonesian Pokémon cards.
Um and we see above so we will put the visual for you here, it might be nicer.
Ah yes, I saw electrobali but in fact it's electrobol.
I had Electrobal myself. Oh yes yes, nothing to see.
Nothing to see. So to keep it simple, I first present the subject and then you
you will ask all the questions because I imagine that you are asking yourself a lot of questions.
that I cut you off then no just for a minute.
Yes, for a minute you can let me talk.
Um I know it's difficult but I'm kidding.
We love each other, don’t worry.
Uh, no animosity. So what is the project in concrete terms?
I'll explain in a minute.
I realized something.
living here in Indonesia for a little over 2 years now, I have been lucky enough
of living in Bali and Jackarta that the Pokémon Company, therefore one of the largest companies
d'Pin, one of the biggest brands currently in Yeah yeah, we
can say that it's almost at the level of Disney now, a little below, but
I think it will go beyond Disney for me.
It's 30% owned by Nintendo, which for me is the biggest entertainment company in the world.
in front of Disney. And Pokémon Company which is a Japanese company like you
you may know launched the Pokémon concept in 99 which very quickly became a
card game and which has become iconic for several reasons.
The first is that it’s a card game.
The second is that people wanted to collect them very quickly and the third
well there was an animated series that was a worldwide hit with video games
which are a worldwide hit each time they are released on Nintendo consoles exclusively.
And so, it has become a social phenomenon.
And here, what is interesting is that we are on a product which is only reserved
to Indonesia, Pikachu Batique.
Um so in fact, he is wearing, as you can see, we will display the visual once again
here he wears what is called the famous Indonesian batique clothing or more precisely
balinet. And so this card is almost unique.
So what are your questions on the subject and what do you think?
what did I do with AI on this subject?
Well, I know because, well, I don't like Pokémon.
I think it's cool. I played the games.
Yeah, I played the game but I think it's pretty cool.
so the batique eh, that's the batique, that's the technique in terms of printing
of the fabric which means that you actually recognize batique because it is the impression
and it's the same on both sides It's also a UNESCO world heritage site
eh. There you have it, there are a lot of them in Indonesia, there are a lot of them in Cambodia too.
Um and so there you go and well in short and in Malaysia too and so well my question I don't know
it's that I imagine that if you if you made this long this long introduction on
the Pikachu so there is absolutely not my subject obviously I think you know a lot
more than me it's I imagine that you have a project with AI with that and you would like that
I react. Yeah, in fact, to keep it simple, I'm going to give you two or three pieces of information.
and that way you can more easily ask questions.
Thanks to the AI, I actually created, I realized that there was an asymmetry.
That is, on this specific product, so actually there are five cards today
accessible. There are different colors, a blue, green, the background actually behind the Pikachu
is of different colors.
And there's one called holo holographic which means it's shiny
and that is the most valuable.
This is always the case in Pokémon cards.
We're not going to do a course on Pokémon cards now, I assure you.
But there is a rarity. There are cards that are worth absolutely nothing, cards that
worth some money. and maps.
There is a Charizard PSA 10 card.
It means PSA, it is the quality level of a card.
She is absolutely perfect.
She has no flaws. It was validated by a service called PSA which is global
and who validates the cards.
And so a card can really create savings on anything in fact.
This is and I can tell you that this economy is very big today.
We are talking in tens of billions.
And there is a card that was sold for 1 million US dollars not 1 million It's worth
a million dollars that.
No, not that one, not that one.
So this one then here is the asymmetry.
So I wanted to talk to you about symmetry.
You see this card it is unsealed.
That means there's still plastic around.
All right. This plastic I will quickly explain.
In fact batique is a concept that was created by the Japanese, so here Pokémon
Company, sorry. And they said, we have a market called Indonesia which
is exploding on Pokémon cards but we have a problem.
Indonesia likes to make counterfeits.
So there began to be counterfeit cards which were sold even in
trunks. Even in shopping malls here in Indonesia, sometimes you find fake
products in trunks.
I don't know if you realize this.
So the Pokémon Company for Hermes bags.
It's the same in fact they have the same problem as a cardboard card in fact
you have counterfeits Exactly.
Exactly. So what happened was they said, the Pokémon Company
said Indonesia is a special market.
We must manufacture the cards ourselves, we must certainly not open a factory in Indonesia,
we will make them ourselves.
We will send them to Indonesia.
And they said, since it's a huge market, we're going to create nice things for the Indonesians
because there’s no work there.
In fact, yes, there is an economy that is being created, so yes, rest assured.
Um, you should know that Pikachu Batique is one of the only cards in the history of
Pokémon company to be so cultural.
Wait, you told me one minute for your pitch there, excuse me, but here we are
already about 2h30 already.
No, I was aiming to understand roughly what your project is with that and well the symmetry
I was talking about it but you suddenly cut me off.
So actually, let's keep it simple.
These cards are worth it, give me one of what we call pitch evalats.
It's that in fact you are in the elevator, you have Yes yes, you have 20 seconds.
Hello Mr. Raphaël, I am very happy to meet you today.
This is my pikachumatic.com project.
We identified a project, something important.
We realized that this card, these cards, these five cards had a value
much more important in the West than in Indonesia where they are sold.
To give you an idea, this card is worth 300,000 rupi, which means €15.
This one a little more, that's it.
But on average, we are between €15 and €100 per card here in Indonesia.
Except that this one, which is worth €15, can be sold for between €80 and €100 in France today.
at the moment when I almost 10 times more what.
Quite. And the price keeps increasing every month.
We have a site which suddenly you said to yourself you have a There is a business.
Okay. And and so you what did you do?
So you have Ah well I did something very simple.
I said that, I repeated that I am absolutely not an expert in business or elsewhere
in ench. So what I did, the whole point of this conversation actually,
I specify who I have Yes. Yes.
which talks about a subject on which I have absolutely nothing to say eh.
But for now but that's why you're in mode you're in mode I told you that
you had gone into journalist mode.
Um, so what we did what I did with artificial intelligence, I
used uh wait until I tell you anything stupid, I used Claude for this for this
this project. It’s a completely side project.
It's just for fun, to have fun.
It makes me laugh. Me, I love collecting things.
I collect figurines, I collect Dragon Ball cards.
There you go, I love it. And so I said to myself well I'm going to take these cards, I'm going to buy some
here sealed therefore with the plastic still around because these are the ones which have the most
of value to sell. And I'm going to sell them in France.
In France. And so I created a website in literally 2 hours which is today
the specific website on Pikachu Bati which is the best in the world.
So. And I could tell you so you can what does it mean then what does it mean?
what did you do with Liam?
You have because I have there is shipping.
Finally you also have to send the cards.
We're not there yet. All right.
It's only on the Yeah.
Today, in any case you have the site, here is the g pe pay site with stripe finally
in any case with a ligou payment system that is simpler than that for the moment.
For now, we are at stage zero, the market test stage.
So I already sold my first cards on eBay quite simply.
No, Pikachucom is a website that will attract people to this specific product.
There are more and more people internationally typing Pikachu BATIC keywords
because they want this card specifically and they want to have information.
This is a very special card.
It has every 6 months, there is a new card that comes out here in Indonesia in
a different city. And you have to know something, to have this card, you have to be
on the big day at the event. That is, you can't buy it online, you can't get it.
You if you want this card at the moment when it is a site which will bring together the events
where the card is likely to be located.
Absolutely. And above all, it's a site where I will buy as many cards as possible and
I will resell them to people who will contact me via the site.
So, to put it simply, it was just a concrete example of an information portal on
on databases, I imagine you recover then in fact I have to recover the
data, I imagine events.
How do you know that the card has this event exactly?
So actually I connected the AI ​​agent that's working on this project.
I connected it to a Pokémon database because.
In fact, they have a website where they put the entire list of events.
So, I tell the agent to go every week to check the latest information
on the subjects and above all I tell him “You check the keywords Indonesia only
because it's a very global thing, it's not yet segmented by country." It will become,
apparently they talked about it recently so it should be.
And it is also connected to a special all-automated collection newsletter
or do you ask it every time to update or does it update
automatically ? Now I have recursing tasks I have recurring tasks which
he will get his data, he will get the newsletters and then he will send me
for the moment it's not 100% automated, I'm not going to lie to you it sends me "Why
It’s not 100% automated?
It's in progress. I take it step by step.
You know, I was always taught a business.
I come from the world of... I'm not saying, is it possible?
Is it possible? I think it's possible.
It's possible. Vi from the startup world.
So I take it step by step.
I keep it as simple as possible. When you say e-commerce, we don't need that.
What I want is someone to send me a message, I want this card.
How much does it cost? That's all.
But in any case if you want batic Pikachu cards, Réy is the one to call.
Ah, it’s an advertising moment in fact.
I didn't understand. All right.
So all of this is sponsored by Réy he's new company which sells Pokémon.
You want me to get fired to sell my stuff.
I will offer cards to the team if the story is basically that you did this with
while you don't know how to code in the first place and so we quote then be careful no I
can't say I don't know how to code that would be lying to my audience I did I
basics in code mainly HTML CSS and Ruby for those who know but these are
basic basics. That's where you are still capable I know I know
read an HTML CSS code in Ruby, that's it.
But I'm not at all an expert compared to even an average developer,
I am very below. Does anyone you think uh can do can do
the same as you? Very good question.
Yes, could. The problem is that he would spend a lot more time because
that I have knowledge of the field of maps.
I have knowledge of Pokémon.
Yes, but of course. No, but I'm not just you uh on another on other cards, a
guy who is passionate about baseball cards, I don't know.
Ah but then there is a market on cards which is currently insane in full
from different fields. At the moment, what works best is obviously One Piece
which is very well known because well it's a manga that exploded and an anime that exploded.
Dragon Ball is still very powerful, Pokémon is exceptional but I advise you
I apologize for specializing in specific cards because there are
has too many cards. You can't collect everything, it's impossible and sell everything.
But yes yes, there is a huge market on cards in what I see in any case it is
that indeed what is interesting is that uh so that each individual can
somewhere become an entrepreneur today and start your own business.
In any case, it gives us extensions of power that we didn't necessarily have before.
Before you had an idea, the idea had to be good but often after that it's
execution. Well but after the execution you had to be a developer associate
you had to be someone who does design who possibly someone who is
good at marketing and there clone accompanied me in all the stages et cetera et cetera
in reference so the advantage is actually uh with AI you can uh all alone
in your room somewhere setting up your Pokémon card business and Claude accompanied me
until the creation of the domain name.
So I knew how to do it but he gave me the best of the best tools, it's not
obvious. There are plenty of people who don't know how to do it.
For me, it remains complicated, it's not complicated, but I suggest that one day
we're making a video where I show you exactly how I did it.
It could be super interesting.
And you will also share with me how you made the book.
That interests me. So, let's change the subject completely.
The agent war, we return to traditional mode.
Um, I want to talk about the agent war.
Advertising page anyway. Excuse me, it lasted a quarter of an hour, eh.
You, do you really want me to get fired?
So suddenly the war of agents Claude Code dipsy and the invisible, I called
that part. I have a first question to ask you on this subject because well
I don't think I'm going to learn from you that we're really in a war
currently in AI for models but also in agents.
All models and agents want to dominate the world and want to have the most
possible customers. It's logical, there are a lot of finances behind it, a lot
of investors. Um do you think that we are heading towards a world where finally
the human will be more than a conductor who will not necessarily or no longer necessarily understand
his instruments, his tools?
So, it's a bit of a general question regarding technology.
Uh me my my grandfather when uh he had lots of cars in his garage because
that my uncles were rally drivers.
So as we are not he does not necessarily receive a lot of money well we were manufacturing
our Finally he took a car and then he took it apart he took it apart et cetera.
But what my grandfather had taught my father was
when he takes the car, he takes the whole car apart and then you put it back together.
That's how you can do it today, you can't really do it with Teslas, you
see ? Because in fact you no longer know what's inside this machine
somewhere. Then in addition a large part in the cloud therefore in the cloud.
So we can see that after a while you inevitably lose with electronics
you lose knowledge, in fact direct knowledge in any case.
Afterwards you can be a hypertechnician and so on.
sure, but technology means that we gradually disconnect a little from reality eh
In any case. And so I would say that's what can happen with AI.
For the moment, the AI ​​is still a little tinkering.
This is how we understand how language models work.
We understand how a language model which is the AI ​​model begins,
like Opus 4.7, it's a language model that goes into a platform called Cloud.
Um then, there is context et cetera, tools, connectors, how everything
it's a box. And for the moment, then also thanks to open source, we can achieve
understand what is happening.
Then Claude, we can also ask him to read us an open source document
to see how it all works.
So in fact, we can come to understand.
Little by little, will we lose consciousness?
Maybe. In any case, there is a risk of opacity.
There is above all me the main risk that I see, it is above all the it is the it is the
concentration of these powers in a few powerful uh which are companies.
Is it okay to give up power over something?
Don Excuse me overall uh whatever the future, we have a technology which
some say it will destroy humanity or Some say it will wipe out all
jobs or not or not.
But that or not, we invest billions in it and we invest in sums that we
has never invested before, except perhaps for nuclear war, well for
nuclear weapons. And and so we I can't say we can't say to ourselves that as much
of money invested with such a high stake but with a probability we go there we all want
go towards super intelligence and what's more we want to go there because otherwise China
going to go there and then Europe is in the middle trying to regulate all that a little but
basically the United States is going all out and China is going all out so all of that is accelerating
with a goal to go there.
So some say yes, we will never achieve super intelligence before 40 years.
We don't know anything about it but all the money is invested to go towards that in any case we
do everything we do, we do everything necessary to move towards the replacement of humanity
or not once again I say or not but as there is a lot of money and especially this
money is concentrated between a few powers that nuclear power is given to one
a certain number of companies, one of which is managed by a Samaltman, I will not entrust him with
my little sister you see and in fact and others we made a video on him by Marc Zuckerberg
who has borderline morality the same as Elon Mcre Once, I have nothing against these people,
but you see, somewhere, I would say, we are obliged to look at whether these people
have the ethical shoulders to hold something this important?
Well no, what. Well, maybe in the tropics a little more, they have ethics but
finally, they still have shareholders.
And then maybe after a while, this power won't be able to stay between
the hands of his boxes. We're going to have to nationalize them.
Perhaps in the United States this will happen.
We don't know. But somewhere, what worries me is the concentration of powers
with such both economic, and existential perhaps also and
geopolitics also also between a few boxes.
That's more what worries me.
So what are we going to be dispossessed of?
I think that the risk in any case and the vigilance to be had is that the individual
and societies, see Europe, because for the moment Europe, we are in the middle of
this thing with not much to give, we're going to talk about it.
Um, we have the risk of being dispossessed of technology.
for the moment the most powerful that humanity has ever produced potentially.
Quite. It's at the nuclear level.
A lot of people say it's on the electricity level.
That is to say that tomorrow we sell intelligence as we sell we will connect to intelligence
as we plug into the current.
Well, but the question of is electricity a common good or not?
Is water a common good or not?
Finally, these are thoughts that we danced about recently.
Uh, so the question arises as to who owns this power which is particularly
company changer. You talked about Europe.
So I really like this subject because many people think that Europe is
completely on the street on artificial intelligence.
I am one of those who say exactly the opposite uh with information, with
data eh, not just because I'm happy to be French and European.
Uh, however, I live, I live very far away.
No, but to return more specifically to the subject of Mistral, there you have it, Mistral and who
is a bit like the unicorn, the horn here is 1 billion, 10 billion et cetera which is
a bit like the big European project which seems to be in any case for the moment the only one capable
of perhaps there you go, I put a lot of quotation marks eh, of perhaps rivaling a
day with the greatest American and Chinese models and others elsewhere because
that the Japanese get into the game too.
and Koreans are starting to invest a lot and others around the world.
Is uh Middle East too?
Yes, the Middle East of course.
So, they have other problems at the moment but yes.
Uh Mistral has signed deals all over Europe recently really every week,
every 10 to 15 days, I have an important new deal that falls in my in my newsletter
specific linked to France and Europe on AI.
And yet at the same time, I like at the same time uh no one really seems
know about this tool and no one really seems to use it too.
You have to be honest.
Do you think it's a bit of a strategy to become the intellectual of Europe?
or rather he would have to put in a little work to really compete
the big mastonodondes on the market?
Well, the main problem with Mustral is the level of investment.
It’s because they don’t have the level of investment.
that we have very high Chinese models but very below it is just very low it is
true very high okay but very low in fact fundamentally compared to this
which is surprising because at the same time Europe is not a small economy so
there is also a problem of there being not enough investment in Europe compared to
its GDP somewhere so I would say that we say yes it is Europe Europe we are small
we are not small compared to the United States compared to compared to China
France is small so somewhere there is an inconsistency in fact in everything and
and one which is also linked to the market and all that.
So I'm not saying it's stupid.
I say that in any case we could, from one point of view, if we take a step back, say
well, it's still I don't think that Mistral is against raising more
times. No no. Then, moreover, Mistral created a deliberately European strategy
even though he is a French champion.
Uh and they have the strategy of sovereignty.
And in fact, they are right since in fact when you have to choose when you are a big
company, that you still have data that is sensitive when you work in
in armament for example or even in technology or in I imagine Talè
for example let's take the example of Tal and here is Talès clearly but Talès who makes
the armament for those who do not know how to finally lead so you have chosen between an average model
uh and uh total sovereignty so if you want and therefore the
the problem of everything that will be hosted on servers even hosted in Europe but
by American operators depends on the cloud.
The cloud out for those who don't know, it's ultimately an American law that says,
you use an American tool, even if the data is stored in Europe, we can
access the data if desired.
If we ask you. So obviously if we ask and Microsoft which even has
his servers in Europe uh well we ask him to do it, he's going to take a huge
fine from Europe.
But between being shot by Donald Trump or a fine by Europe,
I think he will obviously choose his country.
So we have a real problem on this and moreover in fact the issues of lia today
are just sovereignty issues and what just happened with the episode
Trump at all levels shows that in fact the United States is not an ally.
The West no longer recalls anything of Charles de Gaul's sentence of the general.
He said, “Be careful, friends, the United States is not an ally.”
I don't think he said watch out guys, I don't think he said precisely that
sentence there. He is unbearable.
Hello friends. Can you imagine?
Tell me, tell me what he said.
No, the general had more pressure than me.
Obviously, he's the boss, we're trying to make a somewhat young show there.
So yeah. No, but he was the first to withdraw from NATO before
let's come back to it. I think it's SarkoZi who's coming back.
But uh no, what I meant is that in any case the instability makes
that today is a bit what the CIA had planned in its last
report. There is a form of archepilization in any case with blocks like that.
Great report that we recommend, you have to display it.
Yeah. Which is quite interesting because it offers several scenarios that allows you to situate yourself
in relation to that and we see that today we no longer really have any allies, whatever
apart from Europe so Europe becomes a base It depends on the subjects he on the scaf
we have problems with it. So this question of sovereignty is so vital.
Imagine that Trump today said well in fact Nvidia you are no longer part of the countries
reliable for us so you are more entitled to Nvidia.
What do we do? We're in trouble.
And at the same time in Europe, we have SML which is the only company that allows us to do
his fleas. Which box?
It manufactures the large machines that make the chips.
So without Dutch SML, there is no there is no If Europe says stop, well in fact
this is the bottleneck of everything that is happening at the level
of AI today. So obviously we don't have that power.
Anyway, Trump could if he were president of Europe maybe he would do it, you
see, somewhere. We still have very important assets and what is missing today
at the European level, then perhaps it is obviously that there is an awareness
but it is to say that it is vital today to invest in AI technology
sovereign in Europe. It's vital we should emit all our money.
I have the impression in any case a large part of our There is really something
which is happening because there they actually signed deals there
There is a data center being built in France.
There is another one which was signed in Sweden, if I remember correctly, to check the
country, but it is a Nordic country.
Uh Mistral is in the process of installing real capabilities to do what China does if
you want, you have to go faster.
These are factories for manufacturing.
That's right, that's uh we're re-establishing them.
There are battery factories that Rare earths, rare earths, it is said that
it's not eco-friendly. So there are mining projects all over Europe.
They say it's not good and that but anyway, what are you doing at the same time behind?
In Guyana, we also have incredible things to extract.
But hey, I understand the problem, it's not easy.
Yes, it's it's it's it's it's the terrain but at the same time, it's shorter circuits.
In any case also, we obviously have the data centers and the energy because we
has energy which is almost entirely carbon-free, at least in France.
We have a big competitive advantage there, a huge advantage too.
There is nuclear fusion which could make chips.
So, we have uh the uh the the chip photocopiers.
Well somewhere but we actually lack the capacity we manufacture chips near
from Grenoble to Croll 2.
We make chips but it's more for refrigerators, cars and so on.
capacity to produce what China is doing what China is doing
to do without Nvidia. Nvidia is freaking out because they have lost this customer base
left this clientele because of Donald Trump because they know very well that the
China is in the process of manufacturing them itself.
So China understands the question of sovereignty very well.
the United States obviously Europe, there is only Europe which is still between two things.
And that's it and I think that Europe must put this question of sovereignty at the forefront
heart of its strategy, but that means a lot of money, a lot of investment.
The problem is that during the presidential election, the subject of AI will not be at the heart
debates. We're still going to talk about pensions, we're still going to talk about lots of subjects
without what is interesting.
You don't have to either. Of course, the French are interested.
Retirement is normal.
Of course, but it's a subject that is difficult to evaluate.
It's a it's a it's a subject that Wait there, excuse me, I'm cutting you off, but it's
interesting. What do you think it would take for things to really change?
So that people say "Well, OK, there is retirement, there is obviously employment, there is
There is the economy in general obviously, there is the social part too in France.
It remains very important and I am 100% for it.
But how do we say it? Well, now the AI ​​must be the same. I think there is
political will. I think the one thing that's been a constant there ever since
2 years is no problem for juniors.
Oh, it's terrible. So a presidential candidate, he only wins because he
talks about youth. In general, he only wins if he “Ah, you think?” Me, I think that
it's because he speaks old age well rather.
No, when he talks about youth.
not youth. When he talks about youth, what are we going to do for our children?
? All right. Alright. Uh so the future of our children uh as a candidate would say
in the presidential election, it's uh it's it's employment.
What are we training them for?
What do they learn in schools?
and then they go to higher education and then they are not hired because
suddenly these experts are not hired because they arrive on internship and then this
internship well the AI ​​is much more much better than there is I have a lot of companies
who tell me now I'm really hesitant to take on interns or new ones
because I have I have a pattern of a unicorn which since it uses Claude Code put
in place a process center he froze all his and yes and he thinks that in a few
years he will do better with three with three three times fewer people because he
will have integrated there are always humans, there are experts but it is no longer the lords
that we need today.
After all, it is the return of the lords in the companies of the people who
have a lot after the problem is that the lords die after a while
so you have to replace them so how do you replace them if you don't move junior
so there are plenty of problems with everything, whatever the trend for
at the moment the trend is consolidating so the replacement certainly not today
it's not it's not a reality today in any case there are massive investments
which are going towards that so I say when there are massive investments which are going well
you still have to at least ask yourself the question if you want somewhere I think that
the risk of unemployment and the risk of non-hiring and therefore the societal risk, it
is it still worth waving the red flag even if we exaggerate
a little bit because that's what don don d don must actually seize the policies
and so that if it's not a subject that concerns everyone I don't know what maybe
that we will have to stop arguing between the extreme left and the extreme right and we
got into national politics there it's hot and to do politics
politician and perhaps to be interested in real issues which are geopolitical issues
but survival issues also even and again I say I say again I say not I say
not that there is going to be an explosion of unemployment in 3 years, in 5 years, in 10 I hope
not. Then comes the famous creative destruction.
Will we create more jobs?
But anyway, often even if we create more jobs, we don't create them for the
same people. But does even this Chumpeterrian revolution that we talk about,
is it going to happen like this?
Because it's still going much faster than before.
I have company managers who tell me “it’s going too fast, it’s going completely
uh so I think we can't control it.
I don't think anyone controls anything.
Um, there are extremely important geopolitics issues, a lot of money is being invested
at a loss today. So we can no longer even stop the machine because we have spent
too much money. And so I think that the role of a president is to take
take these issues into account and address them.
Whether we have a debate or not at the national level, I don't know.
But in any case, we don't say that at the heart of a presidential program today.
Maybe that doesn't interest people, but anyway, overall uh that's all
everyone should be interested in it.
Quite. Besides, I actually wanted to ask you this question for you.
What is the value of a human in 2030 with all these new technologies arriving,
with the fact that AI agents are perhaps replacing us or not, with
the fact that everything is changing speed, I have never seen this speed
there, we were talking about it earlier, it's crazy and it worries me a lot for
my compatriots and for the general people in the world.
because in fact there is a huge gap but the gap is growing every day
between people who are augmented by AI in one way or another because they
use it really well, they adapted it to their situation and as a result they literally
almost free employees at their services and on the other the so-called normal people who
they say to themselves “No but it’s interesting, it’s fun to do a little research
Google or equivalent but that doesn't interest me that much." So for you, it will be
what is the real value of a human in 2030 and are we finally going to return to culture
general, to all these things what?
Uh yeah, it's an almost philosophical question but in any case laou and
then we will have one last question, we have to because we are almost at the value of a
human. Um, in any case I would rather reformulate the question by saying what
what we need to work on today as humans.
Should we say we must be antifragile in the face of AI?
It is necessary to develop skills which will not be replaceable by AR because
that once again AI replaces humans for me this is as valuable
as the great replacement of Éric Zemour.
It's the same thing. Um, on the other hand, indeed, there are tasks that will be replaced.
There are functions that will be replaced, professions that will be positions that will be
deleted rightly or wrongly also and so on.
The real question is how do I continue to evolve, grow and
to have value in any case in this world.
I think the first thing, the first reflex you must have, is to capitalize
his intelligence. And they say what do you mean by that?
Well, you're the same way when you buy things, you buy things all the time.
Well but if you put money aside on everything you buy, you put €100
aside each month, well after a while you end up with it being capitalized, there is
a snowball effect et cetera.
In the same way, if you want to exercise every day, you don't have to go do it yourself.
a triathlon every 6 months and then you do nothing in between.
Well, usually you practice.
But in any case, you go to sport regularly and therefore you train,
you capitalize on your ability in the same way.
What does capitalizing on your intelligence mean?
say that everything you read today, everything you're going to buy, you're going to watch
on TV, the YouTube videos you see, the articles you read, the thoughts,
the discussion we have between us actually the discussion we have between us actually makes me
in an hour I would have forgotten half of it.
What do I do with that?
Well, I'm recording it.
I record it, I put it in my AI, it makes me clean transcribed, it
gets me that and then she's going to dispatch me, she's going to dispatch me into things
interesting that I could say.
It will complete things and so on.
And in fact, and as a result, you're going to talk about Pikachu Batique in the newsletter.
And I'm going to talk about well maybe not because I still haven't really understood the interest
of the thing. No, he's very cool with it.
You are much smarter than you let on.
I prefer stuffed animals, you see.
And uh, in short, to each their own.
Plush toys have much less collector value on the other hand.
And so I I so what I call so I think that today we need
to use AI to store our notes, our processes and
cetera, to store with us and not with others because we must stop giving
to these uh to these boxes all our intelligence.
We actually buy them GPT chat subscriptions and COD et cetera, but in fact
we get nothing back. So I am for what we call personal AI, that is to say
in fact you have a folder on your machine or on a sovereign server and you have all your
data in it, your notes.
Which means that as soon as you forget something, well you haven't forgotten it because it's
still in it. So you are going to capitalize on everything you have learned, what we call
often the second brains, what we call the Zeltel Casson files, therefore are
ways of taking notes to remember so these are old techniques.
But with artificial intelligence, the advantage is that the AI ​​that will come to your home,
she will become aware of everything that makes you unique, we will say cognitive,
what makes you different.
And so if you because by dint of forgetting everything, storing nothing and only buying
things and to praise et cetera what is given to you to use in fact, you will become
completely transparent.
In fact, you will completely disappear and become a slave and in addition your brain will
often asked what my value is and a company also asks itself the question
to everything I do that I won't be able to do the same so ultimately isn't it
not my biggest competitor?
Yes, but what still remains is your ontie.
It is also the data that you can have, the millions of processes that you have been able to carry out in
your job and so on. Everything that makes you unique.
That's data. These data must be sovereign, they must remain
at your place. Afterwards, you bring an AI model into your house, it works with you and
then it goes away if you need to change it.
There he goes. You can change the AI ​​model.
But this intelligence capital which is made up of all your notes, your processes uh your
way of seeing things, so what will make you unique, don't tell me that it's
in your head because you don't remember it.
And as I told you that we said to ourselves that the brain rebuilds the I think that for
For me, this is the main work we have to do today, is to start saying
what makes me unique?
To start capitalizing on that in a personal AI, therefore a second brain,
a file and AI can help us do just that.
And then afterwards, we obviously have other questions to ask ourselves, but I think that already
That's a good start. Alright.
Last question because we are reaching the end of the 2 hours and it has gone by very quickly.
It feels like it's only been half an hour.
It's great. That means it's a good sign.
In any case, I don't know what you thought about it but Ah, it doesn't matter.
No worries. If you had to start all over again tomorrow, this is the last question.
If you had to start all over again tomorrow, imagine losing everything.
don't worry, I don't want that to happen of course, but imagine, you have more AI,
you have nothing left, you start from zero at the business level, not at the personal level
business only. Which agent would you go with and what idea and why?
What do you think you would do?
Well already there is so it's in a world it's the same world, it's just that you have more
you come back to the beginning as if you came back to the beginning of tuas tuas imagine you have no experience
he has and you discover that today.
So. Ah OK. I think I I think I'll try to understand this
that it is obviously clear clearly to master it.
You are in research mode yeah.
You're a bit of a scientist too.
I'm not a scientist, I'm a journalist.
So we're really here, we're really the information nerds, the journalists
eh. We make drafts of history, drafts of factuality but
uh we have this explorer dimension, this humility in any case to try to be interested
full of understanding. Um, so for me this question of exploration is strong.
Um it is strong because at the same time, once again, I think that uh these technologies
when we understand them well, when we use them well, they can also help us
to emancipate ourselves. Uh me I we I want that tomorrow any person
in a village is capable, he has an idea, a project which does not depend on the hierarchy
social, which do not depend on what his parents, his culture, his religion told him
there, where he was born et cetera or his passport that he is able to set up his project.
not necessarily a business once again or a project it can be an artistic project
it can be here to be able to make your way accomplish your dreams finally make your mistakes
do what so I believe it's it's not the American dream it's it's it's
one of the dreams in any case that technology can bring to individuals with
an environment which is obviously very threatening, very unbalanced, especially today
with a lot of things that I don't like, well we live in a society where it
there are plenty of actors. So either we completely isolate ourselves from this society, or we try
to act with uh and to find anyway even if we want to fight what is happening
today, uh if you don't master AI, you don't master much.
So I think you're excluding yourself somewhere from what's happening.
I think that overall there is every interest in seizing these technologies by
understanding it well, learning not to be absorbed by it, but knowing how to use it
for ourselves. And for that, you have to get to know yourself.
And you were talking about general knowledge, I think that uh the first things that
do when you get involved in this field, buy a paper notebook, a pen, write
your journal in hand or your thoughts in hand.
Read a paper book if you can.
Take some time to go for a walk in nature.
Spend time dreaming. There is there is there is a Latin word called otium which
It's not really just fun.
It's more in fact it's being very active in something that doesn't directly correspond
to our Take the time to stop, to disconnect, to take care of our brain
because faced with these machines, our brain is very It's hot.
And so uh so there you go, I think it's preserving a house in which to
we will be able to approach this world.
Obviously, learn AI, but learn it with a lot of perspective of course.
We'll end there and it's true that it's interesting.
Um, there is a real debate.
I think we could do a second episode on the whole neuronal impact part,
impact on the brain of all these technologies.
There are a lot of studies that are coming out.
We made some of them on video.
In any case, impact on the brain of the use of technologies once again, not necessarily
the technology itself.
Exactly. Exactly. And it's true that I thing for social networks Yeah.
I have an example with two entrepreneurs with whom I work regularly, well
friends what, and who told me uh when when you start to open when you have several
computer or several devices and you start opening several I at the same time and that
you're multitasking, there's a problem.
And I told them be careful because then you go too far and they come
no more sleeping, you see. So that is also a sign that there is something that
not going. Me, I tried to be a crypto trader a few years ago
and I know exactly what the problem is.
You wake up at 3 a.m., you can't sleep, it's a disaster.
Thank you Benois, it was really very interesting.
Very happy to have received you again today.
Um, we'll put your Generation AI links and maybe one or two of your social networks.
You will tell us which ones you want to highlight.
Uh thank you for following us, it was really a great episode.
I am very, very happy to have been able to do this first podcast with Benoît.
Um, if you liked it, tell us in the comments.
If you hated it, say so too.
On the other hand, with the forms, because otherwise, I ban immediately, there will be no
of summons. Um, we listen but we must not, we must respect people.
I think we respect people with this format.
So please respect us.
And of course, if you can share, thank you in advance.
It was Rémy and I'll see you soon for the next one